Register to Paul Dukas Correspondence with Marguerite Hasselmans, and Related Materials
Yale University Music Library
Paul Dukas Correspondence with Marguerite Hasselmans, and Related Materials.
1893-1933
MSS 107
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence between the French composer and critic Paul Dukas (1865-1935) and his friend Marguerite Hasselmans, a concert pianist and Gabriel Fauré's mistress.
Dukas, Paul, 1865-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Sotheby's in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Dukas was born in Paris on October 1, 1865. He studied composition at the Paris Conservatoire with Ernest Guiraud; in 1928, Dukas himself became a professor of composition at the Conservatoire. Like Schumann, Debussy, and Thomson, Dukas was a prominent music critic as well as a composer. He composed a variety of works, mostly for orchestra, voice, or piano. He was not prolific, and he destroyed numerous pieces that did not meet his standards. His most frequently performed composition is The Sorcerer's Apprentice. He died in Paris on May 17, 1935.
Marguerite Hasselmans (1876–1947), daughter of the harpist and composer Alphonse Hasselmans, was a concert pianist and Gabriel Fauré's mistress and constant companion until the end of his days. She was also a close friend of Paul Dukas and Isaac Albéniz. She was beautiful and cultivated; she was interested in philosophy, she read Russian, and she behaved like a modern young woman, for example by smoking and wearing makeup in public. She was appreciated by her contemporaries for her musical talents, her conversation and her delicacy.
Scope and Contents
Paul Dukas' correspondence with Marguerite Hasselmans spans the years 1907 to 1933 and includes 86 autograph letters and 50 postcards adressed to Marguerite Hasselmans, signed with initials ("PD") or in full ("Paul Dukas"). The collection also includes three letters from Paul Dukas to Gabriel Fauré and contains 15 letters and postcards to Marguerite Hasselmans or her father Alphonse and her brother Louis, written by Paul Poujaud, Jules Massenet, Benjamin Godard, Pauline Viardot, Pierre Lalo and Camille Saint-Saëns.
Arrangement
In 2 series as follows: I. Paul Dukas' Correspondence. II. Other Correspondence.
Composers -- Correspondence; Music -- France -- 20th Century; Dukas, Paul, 1865-1935; Hasselmans, Marguerite, 1876-1947; Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924; Godard, Benjamin, 1849-1895; Lalo, Pierre, 1866-1943; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912; Saint-Saëns, Camille, 1835-1921; Viardot-García, Pauline, 1821-1910
- Paul Dukas' Correspondence, 1907-1933; Series I; 86; letters, 50 postcards.; Letters are of different size, some are cross-written, some with drawings.
  Scope and Contents
  Letters and postcards were written from various places: Paris, Royan, Villefranche-sur-Mer, Cannes, Brussels, Fontainebleau, Salzburg and elsewhere. It is a characteristically witty series, especially in the collection of postcards, where the composer often sends a humorous line or remark, sometimes relating to the image printed on the reverse, enclosing frivolous and irreverent poems. It is also a revealing correspondence, all the more since Paul Dukas was a notably private person. This collection of letters to Marguerite Hasselmans contains intimate insights into his private and professional life, discussing his works, including Ariane et Barbe-Bleu, the symphony, la Peri amongst others; his friendship with Albéniz (deploring his loss), Fauré, Paul Claudel, Alfred Cortot, Widor, Saint-Saëns, Jacques Durand, Florent Schmitt, Poujaud, and his family, including announcing his decision to marry Suzanne Pereyra, the death of his brother, the anniversary of his father's death and other family events; the musical life of Paris and his work as a critic. As the companion of Fauré and a musician herself, Marguerite Hasselmans was a uniquely-placed correspondent for Paul Dukas.Their correspondence continued and even intensified after Fauré's death.
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Autograph letter signed Paul Dukas
    - Paris, 1907; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907 May 15; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Autograph letter signed Paul Dukas, envelope
    - Paris, 1907 June 17; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907 September 6; 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907 September (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Autograph postcard signed PD
    - Paris, 1907 October (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Paris, 1907 December 7; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1908 February 10; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1908 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1908 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph poscard signed PD
    - Paris, 1908 August 9; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph letter signed paul Dukas
    - Paris, 1908 November 8; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brussels, 1908 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph postcard signed Paul Dukas
    - Brussels, 1908 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1909 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1909 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1909 July 8; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1909 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1909 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 February 8; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 May 19; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 May; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 August; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Salzburg, 1910 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 October 24; 1; page, envelope (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Paris, 1910 October 26; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Autograph letter signed PD
    - Paris, 1910 December 7; 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1911 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1911 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Autograph postcard
    - Paris, 1911 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1911 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1911 October 7; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 ?; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Autograph card signed Paul Dukas
    - Paris, 1912 March 23; 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 May 20; 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 June 17; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 July 13; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Florence, 1912 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1912 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 January 24; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Autograph poscard signed Paul Dukas
    - Paris, 1913 April 19; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nîmes, 1913 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris, 1913 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Paris (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Avignon, 1914 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Montpellier, 1914 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Moulins, 1914 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1914 May 31; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1914 August 29; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1914 December 14; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1915 December 11; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1916 January 2; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1916 April 19; 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Autograph letter signed PD, envelope
    - Paris, 1916 July 26; 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1916 July 30; 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Paris, 1916 September 24; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1917-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Paris, 1917; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Paris, 1917 April 8; 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Paris, 1917 August 15; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cannes, 1917 December 11; 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Paris, 1918 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Villefranche-sur-Mer, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Villefranche-sur-Mer, 1919 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nice, 1919 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cannes, 1919 December 11; 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Paris, 1920 January 25; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Villefranche-sur-Mer, 1920 April 8; 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Autograph letter signed PD (cross-written)
    - Villefranche-sur-Mer, 1920 December 10; 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ?, 1920? (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ? (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1921 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hardelot, 1921 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fontainebleau, 1922 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fontainebleau, 1922 September 28; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Royan, 1924 October 28; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1925 ? 10; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1925 April 26; 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1925 April 28; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Royan, 1925 August 3; 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1925 August 23; 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Royan, 1925 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Autograph postcard signed Paul Dukas (cross-written)
    - Royan, 1925 October 11; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Royan, 1925 November 9; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Paris, 1925 December 24; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1926 January 2; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1926 January 10; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1926 March 13; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph letter signed Paul Dukas (cross-written)
    - Paris, 1926 May 4; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Nîmes, 1926 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sète, 1926 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Royan, 1926 June 3; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1926 August 18; 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1926 September 17; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph letter signed PD (cross-writen)
    - Paris, 1926 October 29; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph letter signed PD, envelope (cross-written)
    - Paris, 1926 November 16; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chambéry, 1926 ? (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1927 June 29; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph letter signed Paul Dukas (cross-writen)
    - Royan, 1927 July 10; 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Royan, 1927 July 29; 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1927 August 23; 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Paris, 1927 November 9; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1928 March 23; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1928 May 4; 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Royan, 1928 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Autograph postcard signed PD, envelope
    - Paris, 1928 August 26; 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1928 December 23; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1931 June 12; 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1931 June 19; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1931 August 8; 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1931 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Empty envelope
    - Royan, 1931 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Autograph postcard signed Paul Dukas, envelope
    - Paris, 1931 November; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Autograph letter signed Pd (cross-written)
    - Paris, 1931 November 17; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Paris, 1931 November 24; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Royan, 1932 September 18; 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Royan, 1933 July 28; 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Royan, 1933 August 24; 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ?, 1933? (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Visiting card+ autograph letter, envelope
  - Correspondence to Gabriel Fauré, 1910-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Salzburg, 1910 August 21; 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Pisa, 1912 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Royan, 1922 June 25; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Other correspondence, 1893-1913; Series II; 6 letters, 9 postcards
  - Correspondence to Marguerite Hasselmans, 1895-1913 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lalo, Pierre, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph card signed Pierre Lalo
    - Paris, 1912 November 16; Lalo, Pierre, 1866-1943; 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph letter signed Pierre Lalo, envelope
    - Egreville, 1898 July 4; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Massenet, Jules, 1905 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph letter + visiting card
    - Poujaud, Paul, 1910 July 11; 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph letter signed Paul Poujaud
    - Poujaud, Paul, 1912 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph postcard signed P. Poujaud.
    - Poujaud, Paul, 1913 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph postcard signed Paul Poujaud.
    - Saint-Saëns, Camille, 1903 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph card, envelope
    - Paris, 1895 May 29; Viardot-García, Pauline, 1821-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph postcard signed P. Viardot
    - Paris, 1895 October 12; Viardot-García, Pauline, 1821-1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph postcard signed PV
  - Correspondence to Alphonse Hasselmans, 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - M. de Hastfer, 1901 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Paris, 1893 April 14; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912; 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Autograph letter signed J. Massenet
    - Egreville, 1905 July 27; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912; 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Autograph letter signed J. Massenet, envelope
    - Morlaix, 1905 July 31; Pierné, Gabriel, 1863-1937; 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Autograph letter signed Gabriel Pierne
  - Correspondence to Louis Hasselmans, 1893-1911 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Godard, Benjamin, 1893 May 16; 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Autograph letter signed Benjamin Godard
    - Paris, 1911 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Autograph postcard signed ?